[SQUEAKING]
[RUSTLING]
[CLICKING]
PROFESSOR: Today, we
have a special guest
lecturer, Professor Andrew Lo.
A lot of you may have
already known Professor Lo,
but I still will make
a quick introduction.
So Professor Lo is professor at
the MIT Sloan Business School
for many years.
He's also the director of
the Laboratory for Financial
Engineering and a
principal investigator
with MIT CSAIL, which is the
Computer Science and Artificial
Intelligence Lab.
He also has many other
active involvement with, say,
just a couple of examples.
Santa Fe Institute
and NBER, which
is a National Bureau
of Economic Research.
And Professor Lo's research
areas are very broad too.
So I think it will be too long
for me to read through them.
I think instead of
that, I will pass it
on to Professor Lo
for today's lecture.
ANDREW W. LO: All right.
Great.
Thanks very much, Jake.
Thank you, Peter, for
inviting me to 18.642.
Happy to be here.
And I'm going to be talking
to you about some big ideas,
and some big
challenges, particularly
for your generation, because
our generation has created
the problems that
your generation is
going to need to deal with.
And so what I'm
hoping to do today
is also to give you some
of the tools by which you
can deal with some of those
problems, problems like climate
change, like
dealing with cancer,
various kinds of energy demands
that are growing exponentially
even as we speak.
So by background, I'm
a financial economist
by training and trade.
Got my PhD at Harvard in
economics, financial economics.
Then ended up teaching
at the Wharton School.
And for the last 35 years,
I've been teaching at MIT
at the Sloan School
in the finance group.
And when I teach my
first-year MBAs in finance,
I start off by
telling them, finance
is the most important
subject you will ever
take at a business school.
And I acknowledge that
my other colleagues
in departments like accounting,
and marketing, operations
research, they may feel the
same way about their subject.
But the key difference
is that in my case,
I happen to be right.
And the reason is because
no matter what you do,
no matter what
field you go into,
no matter what industry
you choose for your job,
at some point or
another, when you want
to do something really
important, really
transformative, you
will need money.
And at that point, you will
be speaking my language.
You will need to understand the
basics of financial analysis,
things like cost of
capital, net present value
calculations, and so on.
So in this very short
and compressed lecture,
I'm going to give you
an exposure to all
of those concepts in the
context of dealing with some
of society's biggest issues.
And I'm going to focus
on two in particular.
One is in biomedicine,
and the other
is going to be in energy,
particularly fusion energy.
So let me first start
with an observation
on the first set of examples.
And that is that biomedicine
is at an inflection point.
Now some of you who are
biology majors, you know this.
Actually, do we have any biology
majors here in this class?
Anybody doing anything
in bioengineering?
How about chemical engineering?
Chemistry?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
ANDREW W. LO: OK.
All right.
Well, people do math
and other subjects.
But anyway, it turns out
that in biomedicine, things
are different than
they've ever been
in the history of the field.
And I'm going to give
you two examples of that.
The first example has to do
with these two kids, Caroline
and Cole Carper.
They were born with a rare
condition known as Leber's
congenital amaurosis.
It's a single-gene mutation,
a typo in your DNA,
that causes blindness
starting at birth.
You're born with a
normal pair of eyes,
but this mutation
prevents your eyes
from producing a very
important protein.
And without the protein,
you start to go blind.
So by the time you're
six months old,
you are legally blind
from that point on.
And so these two kids were part
of a clinical trial in 2016,
started by a Philadelphia-based
drug company called
Spark Therapeutics, that used
a really remarkable therapy
to try to deal with
their genetic mutation.
It's a treatment
known as gene therapy.
And the way it works is this.
You take the correct
version of the gene
that these two kids don't have.
You insert it into a virus.
And then you inject
the virus into the back
of the eyes of these two kids.
One-time injection.
And what happens is the
virus infects the cells,
and picks the correct
gene, and swaps it
with the incorrect
version in those cells.
And from that point
forward, these kids' cells
in the back of their eyes
start producing this protein.
And let me tell
you what Caroline
said a few days after she
received the injection.
"I went outside
when it was snowing,
and I was like, oh, I
can see the snowflakes.
It was really cool to actually
see something that I've never
seen in my life before."
One-time injection,
and now, she can see.
The second example has to
do with a disease known
as Canavan disease.
So this is also a
single-gene mutation, a typo.
And what this disease
does is pretty subtle.
It prevents your
nerve cells from being
able to maintain the myelin
sheath that basically provides
the insulation for
that nerve cell.
Now you all know that
nerve cells have a nucleus,
and they've got an axon,
right, this long string that
conducts electricity, and allows
you to basically take an impulse
and transmit it to various
parts of your body.
And the purpose of this myelin,
myelin is a kind of fat.
The purpose of this
fatty sheath that
goes on the outside of every
nerve cell is insulation.
It's like a wire that has to
have some kind of insulation
to prevent the electrical
impulses to cross
to other wires.
When that happens, you
get short circuits.
And obviously,
that's a bad thing.
Well, it turns out that kids
with this single-gene mutation,
after they're born, the
myelin sheaths in their body
begin to degrade.
And so the electrical impulses
start to short circuit.
And so you have a hard time
controlling your muscles.
And so generally, these
kids have a lifespan
of about 10 to 12 years.
This is an example
of a Canavan patient.
He's probably close
to his end of life.
They generally
don't grow beyond 15
just because it becomes
harder and harder
to control your
breathing, your heartbeat.
All of the bodily functions
that we take for granted
become much more difficult
in Canavan patients.
You'll notice that he's
leaned back on his wheelchair.
The reason is that his head
tends to be larger than normal.
This hyperencephaly,
your head gets bigger,
is part of the symptom
of the disease.
And at some point, your neck,
because there's no muscle tone,
because you can't use the
muscles because of the nerve
impulses that get
short circuited,
it's very easy to snap the neck
if you just lean over like this.
And so you have to always
be in a prone position,
and your head protected
by these cushions.
There's lots of other
terrible symptoms.
Let me tell you what they are.
Children with Canavan disease
cannot crawl, cannot walk,
cannot sit, or talk.
Over time, they may
suffer seizures,
become paralyzed,
developmentally delayed,
blind, and have
trouble swallowing.
Deafness may also
result. Many children
do not live past the age of 10.
And at present time, there is
no cure for Canavan disease.
Treatment involves
managing the symptoms.
And so the typical
Canavan patient,
the disease generally affects
you starting at birth.
But in some cases, it can get
progressively worse over time.
The doctors that know how
to diagnose this disease,
typically what they
tell their parents
is, go home and love your child.
That's their treatment.
That's it.
That's all they can do.
So it turns out
that you can treat
this disease using the same
technique, gene therapy.
Take the correct version of
the gene, put it into a virus,
inject the virus, in this case,
into the brains of these Canavan
patients.
And well, I'm going to show you
a video clip of what happens
with one particular patient.
This is patient number
three, I believe.
And what you're going to
see is a clinical trial
of the patient
before the treatment,
after she's diagnosed.
So they know that she's
got this mutation.
You can see the symptoms
that are developing.
And the frustrating
thing is that you
are born relatively normal.
But because your body can't
maintain the myelin sheaths,
you begin to degenerate
over a period of time.
So let me show you
what's going on here.
So this is June 2022 just
before the treatment.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- So this is the patient.
- You eating your blueberries?
- And she's about one year old.
And so at this age, you
should be able to move around.
But look at her hand motions,
and how jerky her control is.
It's going to take
her quite a while
just to grab one blueberry
and put it in her mouth.
So this is going to
get much, much worse
at this particular
rate of degeneration.
[END PLAYBACK]
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- Now this is about six months
after that one-time injection.
- Wow.
Look at you trucking along.
Come on.
- She's actually walking, even
though it's with a walker.
She's actually able to walk.
Now you can tell that
there's still slow--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
- She can't walk on her own yet.
But this is only six
months after the treatment.
OK?
Now this is just
around the same time.
She is now getting ready to
actually stand on her own.
And this uses an enormous
amount of core muscles.
You probably all know you
have to exercise your core.
So she's developing
core muscle strength.
She can't quite do it
yet, but she's close.
Very close.
And--
- There you go.
- There she goes.
She's just about to do it.
That's it.
For the very first time, she
actually stood up on her own.
Amazing.
Now this is a month after that.
She is walking
without the walker.
She can't do it all on her
own yet, because remember,
it's only been about
seven or eight months
since her body is able to deal
with this myelin sheath problem.
But way better.
Now this is about
nine months later.
She's on a bike, which
is extraordinary.
And she's motioning to her
dad to give her a push,
and to help her out.
And here she is just a
few months ago this year.
So this is now about a
year and three months
after that dose of gene therapy.
She's about to be able
to walk on her own
for the very first time.
There has been no
Canavan patient
in the history of
the disease that
has ever been able to do this.
And so this is remarkable,
remarkable progress.
- Can you blow me a kiss?
[KISS SOUND]
Thank you, honey.
- She is actually reading now.
She's starting to learn the
letters of the alphabet,
and she's responsive.
She can actually interact.
This is extraordinary.
[END PLAYBACK]
ANDREW W. LO: The
blind shall see.
The lame shall walk.
That's a phrase that
we usually associate
with religious experiences.
But it's happening.
It's happening now thanks
to the miracles that
are being developed by these
scientists and clinicians.
And our colleagues, Phil
Sharpe, Susan Hockfield,
and Tyler Jacks, they
published a paper in 2016
to describe this new world
that we're living in.
They call it, convergence.
The convergence of the life
sciences, physical sciences,
and engineering,
all of these fields
are coming together to be
able to do things that people
were not able to do before.
The other term that
people in biomedicine use
is the omics revolution.
All of these omics have
experienced tremendous progress
over the last even five
years, never mind 10 or 20.
And genomics, the science
of sequencing your genes,
epigenomics, the on-off switches
that cause certain genes to be
switched on, and others to be
switched off, transcriptomics,
the various different ways that
you can turn sequences of genes
into proteins that
are in your body,
proteomics the 20,000 to 25,000
proteins that are being produced
every day by your body.
Metabolomics, the
chemical reactions
that make life possible.
And finally, most recently,
microbiomics, the colonies
of bacteria that inhabit our
bodies that keep us healthy.
All of these omics have given
us tremendous new knowledge
based upon research that's been
going on thanks to convergence,
with the exception of one.
There is one omics that's been
the bottleneck to progress.
And you know what that omics is?
Economics.
Because you got
to pay for stuff.
And we're using the same old
stuff, the same old business
models, to try to do
those kinds of financings.
So what I want to tell
you about is a challenge
that economics is
facing, and how we
can get around that challenge.
And the challenge is
this, the valley of death.
When I first started getting
interested in health care,
I would talk to scientists, and
doctors in Boston, Cambridge.
We have a lot of them, as you
know, very, very good ones.
And I would ask them, why
isn't there more progress?
And it keeps telling
me about the valley
of death, the valley of death.
So I'm thinking, what
does southern California
have to do with
progress in biomedicine?
And then they tell
me, no, no, no.
It's not a place.
It's actually a
metaphysical concept
of the period between
scientific experiments
at university and
medical centers,
and first in human
clinical trials.
That period in between
those two milestones
is the valley of death,
meaning that it's
really hard to raise money to
fund those kinds of things.
And so money is
something that I've
spent a lot of time studying.
So my initial reaction was, why?
Why is it the case that
there is a valley of death?
I just assumed that if
there was a patient in need,
and there was some technology
that could help that patient,
that magically,
money would appear
to fund the drug or a
device, and everything
would be hunky dory.
Turns out that that's not
really how the world works.
And the more I studied
the problem, the more I
realized that actually,
the valley of death
exists not just in health
care, but in many fields
because of increasing
risk and uncertainty.
Now what do I mean by
risk and uncertainty?
I think you all
know what risk is.
Risk is the kind of randomness
that we can parameterize.
So normal distribution, gamma
distribution, chi squared.
We can figure out
the probability laws
of risky things.
But the uncertain
things, those are
what economists refer to
as the unknown unknowns,
because nobody's ever
done them before.
There's no data.
So you can't assess
the probability
that this could possibly happen.
And so that's the challenge
that the valley of death
ultimately needs to overcome.
Because drug development
is a very lengthy process,
as some of you
may know, you have
to go through clinical testing.
And because of that process,
there are three things about
investing in drug
development that investors
have to get their arms around.
One, it costs a
large amount of money
to do the testing, hundreds of
millions to billions of dollars,
in order to get
one drug approved.
Second, that process is
generally very, very unlikely
to succeed.
Low probabilities of success.
And third, it turns out
that developing a drug
can take 10 to 15 years
from beginning to end.
So if you compare that
with developing an app,
how many of you have actually
developed an app already?
Yeah, so I imagine that it
doesn't take you $100 million
to do that.
And it doesn't take
you 10 or 15 years.
you a whole team
of people, where
you're going to fail
with a probability
of whatever, 95%.
So that's the problem
with investing in this.
And so I'm going to give
you an example of why
this is so challenging by asking
you to think about investing.
Some of you may already have
invested, especially given
that we're at MIT.
I often encounter
undergraduates who
are actually quite accomplished
traders and portfolio managers.
But let me give you
the example that I
give my first-year MBA students,
and see how you do with this.
I show them four different
financial investments.
I don't tell them what they are,
or even over what time period
they span.
I just tell them,
this is what happens
when you put a dollar into
it, and you leave it there
for an unspecified,
multi-year investment horizon.
The green line turns
a dollar into $2.00.
Not very rewarding, but
not particularly risky.
The red line turns $1.00 into
$5.00, way more rewarding,
but way more volatile,
lots of ups and downs.
The blue line turns a
dollar into about $8.00,
the most rewarding of all,
but also the most volatile.
And the black line,
somewhere in the middle.
Not the most rewarding,
but relatively reasonable
amount of risk.
So if you could have only
one of these investments,
you can't mix and
match them, if you only
can have one to put
your life savings,
or better yet, to invest your
grandparents' retirement money,
and you had to do it for them,
they asked you to help them,
which would you pick?
How many of you would pick
the green line to invest?
Wow, no takers?
OK, how about the red line?
How many people would
take the red line?
No takers for the red line?
I want you to
remember this moment,
because I think
some of you may want
to call your brokers
afterwards when I tell you
what the red line is.
How about the blue line?
How many people want
to do the blue line?
OK, we got one or two
entrepreneurs in here,
or hedge fund manager.
OK good.
And then now the black line.
How about the black line?
Yeah, by far the most popular
choice in my MBA class as well.
And when I ask
them why, they say,
well, it's got the best trade
off between risk and reward.
Yeah, question.
AUDIENCE: Isn't the black
line [INAUDIBLE] Ponzi scheme?
ANDREW W. LO: Really?
I don't know.
Let's see.
First of all, let me tell
you what the four assets are.
And we'll talk about that.
The four assets are the
green line, treasury bills,
safest asset in the world, at
least for the next few weeks.
We'll see whether the
budget discussions go well.
As long as we agree to pay back
our debts, yes, safe asset.
But you know what?
You put your money
in it in 2008,
you would have earned
pretty much nothing.
And actually, you
would have earned
less than nothing
because of inflation
if you look at the real return.
All right.
The red line that
none of you picked,
that is the US stock market.
I bet you some of
you may already have
an investment in the S&P 500.
Right?
But if you didn't pick it, or
if you did pick it in 2008,
congratulations.
You would have done
just fine since then.
Very, very good return.
The blue line that only
one of two of you picked,
that is the single
pharmaceutical company, Pfizer,
one of the largest pharma
companies in the world.
And if you had picked
Pfizer in 2008,
well, double congratulations.
You would have done
spectacularly well since then.
Lots of volatility,
but really quite well.
Now the black line, that
is the returns to a fund
called the Fairfield Sentry
Fund, which most of you
have probably never heard of.
But that was the feeder fund for
the Bernie Madoff Ponzi scheme.
So quite right.
You got the correct answer.
I had to stop it in 2008 because
the Ponzi scheme ended up
blowing up then.
Now I show this
example to students
because I want to
explain to them something
very common about human nature.
And that is that we
all, as investors, we
want high yielding,
low-risk assets.
And we have a name in
finance that describes it.
It's called the Sharpe
ratio, after Bill Sharpe,
the Nobel-Prize-winning
economist from Stanford,
who pointed out that people
care about the expected return
of an investment above
T-bills per unit of risk
that they're taking.
They want to have the highest
expected return per unit risk.
High Sharpe ratios.
So what's the Sharpe ratio
of these investments?
Well, it's 0.33 for
the S&P, point--
sorry, 0.34 for Pfizer, 0.33
for the S&P. And on paper,
the Ponzi scheme had a Sharpe
ratio an order of magnitude
higher.
And that's how Bernie
Madoff suckered
all of these poor investors to
put money with him. $50 billion
of investor money that
he essentially stole
because of this common fact.
Now it turns out
that biomedicine
has had a Sharpe ratio
that's been declining
over the last several decades
not because the numerator is
unattractive.
There are many biotech companies
that just do super well.
But the problem
is the numerator.
The numerator is
growing even faster.
The risk, as well
as the uncertainty
is growing as we become more
sophisticated about the science
and medicine of disease.
And so we need to figure out how
to increase the Sharpe ratio.
That's the goal.
So I know this is a math class.
So I could not possibly
do a presentation here
without giving you at
least one equation.
So I'm going to give
you an equation.
And it's going to be
a very difficult math
challenge about how you can
increase the Sharpe ratio.
It turns out there are two ways
of increasing the Sharpe ratio.
And let me tell you,
for those of you who
aren't as mathematically
gifted as I am,
you can increase the
numerator, or you
can decrease the denominator.
Those are the two ways.
Now of course, in
my MBA class, I
have to have a student who
raises his hand and says,
Professor Lo, there's
actually a third way.
And I said, oh, really?
He said, yes, you can do both.
So yes, I agree.
You can do both.
It turns out that
we are doing both.
Better science,
better engineering,
better organizational
structures, on and on.
All of those are designed
to increase the numerator
and decrease the denominator.
But the one set of
techniques that have not
been used as much in biomedicine
as well as in other industries
that I'm about to tell you
is new financing and business
models.
And that's the interesting
opportunity for mathematicians,
believe it or not.
There are ways of constructing
new business models
using math that could actually
change the risk-reward trade
offs of these investments.
So let me show you.
I'll give you an example.
Suppose I give
you an opportunity
to invest in a new
fund that I'm creating.
I need $200 million
to launch my fund.
And I'm going to be
investing in all sorts
of special technologies
that only I have access to.
You don't, So it's proprietary.
It's going to take me 10
years before I give you
any payoff whatsoever.
So don't bother asking me before
the decade is out whether or not
I'm going to give
you anything back.
It's going to take
at least that long.
And in full disclosure,
the likelihood
that I give you
anything back is 5%.
95% of the time, I'm not going
to be able to produce anything
after 10 years.
OK?
How many of you
would invest with me?
AUDIENCE: Depends on the return.
ANDREW W. LO: Thank you.
Most of you didn't even
bother raising your hand.
But you, you want to
know what the return is.
Fair enough.
That's absolutely right.
For most of my MBA students,
they don't bother asking.
When they hear $200 million,
wait 10 years, 95% failure rate?
No thank you.
Not interested.
But I will get one or
two MBA students who
will ask, what's the return?
So let me tell you.
These are the
back-of-the-envelope
calculations for what a single
anti-cancer drug will do
in terms of potential
revenues and success rates.
It takes about $200 million
to do the clinical trials.
It takes about 10
years to do them.
And in oncology, the
historical success rate
is actually a
little less than 5%.
3.4%.
But I'm going to use
5% as round numbers.
If you are successful, though,
in the case of cancer drugs,
you will get $2 billion of
revenues from years 11 to 20.
Why 11 to 20?
Well, because it takes 10
years to develop a cancer drug.
So if you're successful,
then starting in year 11
is when you begin to
generate cash flows.
And why until year 20?
It's because that's how
long a patent lasts.
After year 20, your
patent is gone.
And people can compete with you,
and your profits go way down.
Two billion, two billion, two
billion from years 11 to 20.
That is equivalent to a
single payday of $12.3 billion
in year 10.
OK, so now let me ask you
the question one more time.
I need $200 million up front.
Wait 10 years.
95% of the time, I'll give you
nothing, maybe a warm handshake
and goodbye.
And 5% of the time, I'll give
you a check for $12.3 billion
in year 10.
How many of you
would invest in that?
AUDIENCE: It would
depend on [INAUDIBLE].
ANDREW W. LO: No.
No.
I'll take whatever--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
ANDREW W. LO: Whatever
money you have.
How many of you?
All right.
I'm getting one or two
hands, but not a lot.
You're not all interested,
because for most of you,
it was way too risky.
It takes too long, probability
of success is too low,
and it's just not
your cup of tea.
And sure enough, if we
calculate the rate of return,
this is an expected rate of
return over this 10-year period
of about 12% with the standard
deviation of 423.5% for a Sharpe
ratio of close to 0.
Nobody's interested in
this, or very few people.
So this is where
financial engineering
can make a difference, and
where math comes into play.
A very, very small
amount of math.
Instead of investing
in one of these drugs,
why not invest in, oh, I
don't know, 150 of them
all at the same time?
If we did that, if we
invested 150, you might say,
well, wait a minute.
That takes 150 times 200
million, which is $30 billion.
That's not the kind of math
that would make anybody excited.
$30 billion.
Where are you going
to get $30 billion?
And as an economist, I have a
very simple answer for that.
The answer is, assume
we have $30 billion.
I'll come back to
this in a minute.
But if we had $30
billion, and if we
assume that the 150 projects
are statistically independent
and identically
distributed, and I'll
come back to that assumption
later, if that's the case,
then the expected rate of
return for the portfolio
is the same because
they're identical projects.
But the risk now goes
down by the square root
of the number of projects.
Why?
Because the variance
of the sum is
the sum of the variances
when they're IID.
And so if the variance is the
sum of the individual variances,
take the square root of that
to get the standard deviation.
That's why it goes down by the
rate of the square root of 150,
which gives you a
34.6% risk rate.
Now if I calculate the
Sharpe ratio of this,
I'm getting a Sharpe ratio that
is an order of magnitude higher.
How many of you would
invest in this fund?
Show of hands.
I'm getting a lot more hands.
That's where I'm going
to get the money.
I don't have 30 billion,
but you do in the aggregate.
If I can make this investment
attractive enough to get you
to put some of
your 401(k) money,
or some of your summer
internship money,
into a fund like this, I
can raise $30 billion very,
very quickly.
Now the question is, can you
really raise $30 billion?
And the answer, of
course, is it depends.
It depends on these
calculations that I just did.
It depends on the math
underlying this portfolio.
The mathematics will tell you
whether or not this is feasible.
So I'll give you an example,
where not only should
it work, but it
actually does work.
And the example has to
do with rare diseases.
So I gave you two
examples of rare diseases
at the beginning, Canavan
disease, and Leber's
congenital amaurosis.
Turns out, there are roughly
12,000 different rare diseases.
And so individually,
a rare disease
may have a small patient
population like cystic fibrosis,
hemophilia, Lou
Gehrig's disease,
or a number of other diseases.
But in aggregate, there are more
than 30 million Americans that
are suffering from one
of these 12,000 diseases.
I suspect that
somebody in this room
knows a friend or
a family that's
suffering from a rare disease.
Anybody?
Just show of hands.
Do you?
Yeah.
So it is clear that it may
be rare for any individual,
but it is not rare
over a population,
because of just the number of
mutations that are out there.
And so for a lot of reasons,
it's actually relatively easier
to develop a drug for
a rare disease, both
because typically,
we know what's wrong.
There's a very serious problem.
And you can trace the origins
to one particular organ,
and within that organ, to
one particular mechanism,
and to that mechanism,
one particular gene.
So you know a lot about it.
But the other reason it's often
more successful to develop
these therapeutics is because
it doesn't cost as much money
because it's a rare population.
So when you run the
clinical trials,
you can run them with a
smaller number of people
and still be able to
demonstrate that the drug works,
like the case for
Spark Therapeutics.
In the case of that Leber's
congenital amaurosis,
I think they got an FDA
approval with something
like 30 or 40 patients.
That's it, 30 or 40 patients
in the clinical trial.
And when they were able
to restore their sight,
the FDA said, you don't
need to do any more testing.
We're ready to prove it.
This is an amazing drug.
But the key
component is the fact
that because these
rare diseases are
so different from
each other, there's
very little correlation
in the successes
and failures of different
therapeutic programs.
So when you calculate
the variance of the sum,
it really is the sum
of the variances.
If we don't have
correlation, then
can anybody tell
me what the formula
is for the variance of a
sum of random variables?
AUDIENCE: Sum of the variance?
ANDREW W. LO: Sum
of the variance.
AUDIENCE: It's covariance.
ANDREW W. LO: Exactly.
How many covariances?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
ANDREW W. LO: A lot of them.
Exactly.
Because you've got A
versus B, A versus C,
A versus D, B versus C,
B-- all the combinations.
And so it turns out that
when there's correlation,
it's almost always positive.
And so when you
calculate the variance
of a sum of a portfolio
of typical investments,
you're getting not just
the individual variances,
but all the pairwise
covariances.
If there aren't any
pairwise covariances,
that's where the risk
reduction comes from.
And so rare diseases have this
really cool property that I
have to admit, I'm quite proud.
I was the one who wrote a
paper that recognized it.
Frankly, I didn't think
it was that big a deal
except for this
particular application.
But it turns out that
in the biomedical field,
nobody had ever
thought about this.
The fact that because the
diseases were so different,
you ought to develop them
not separately, but together
in a single portfolio to
get the risk reduction.
So instead of $30 billion, you
only need 400 to 500 million.
Instead of 150 projects,
you only need 10 or 20
to get diversification.
And so what did I do
with this information?
I wrote a paper.
That's what we do in academia.
Published a paper, ran
a Monte Carlo simulation
to show that if you actually
used relevant industry numbers,
the kind of rate of
return you're looking at
is around 22% per year.
And with the
volatility, that could
be quite a bit lower
than that, meaning
a Sharpe ratio greater than 1.
Now you can ask Jake afterwards
about whether or not a Sharpe
ratio greater than 1 is good.
As a professional investor and
a risk manager for A Harvard
management company, he
can attest to the fact
that this is a very
attractive and very rare
kind of opportunity.
But remember, there are
12,000 rare diseases.
So it doesn't seem
that rare to me.
So the question is,
does this really work?
And the reason I wrote the paper
was because I wanted people
to try it out.
And I got a phone call shortly
after the paper came out
from a former student of mine.
Somebody who was a PhD in
chemical engineering here at MIT
took one of my courses when
he was here, then went on,
and became a biotech VC, and
called me up, said, Professor
Lo, I read your paper.
Really interesting.
Would you mind rerunning
your simulations,
not with your assumptions,
but with mine?
And I said to this former
student, of course.
I'd be happy to.
You know a lot more about
the industry than I do.
I'm just using
industry averages,
whereas you actually
have hard data based
upon your own
portfolio investments.
So we ran a model with his
parameters instead of mine.
And the results,
they look better.
And so then I suggested
a few other tweaks
based upon what he was
telling me about the industry,
the way it works in his field.
And we ran my version, and
it looked better still.
Over six months, I think we
ran 35 different versions
of this model.
And at the end of that six-month
period, he came into my office
and said, I just wanted to
let you know, I quit my job
yesterday.
I'm going to do this.
I'm going to build this company.
And I got to tell you, that
scared the hell out of me.
I had never had that effect
on any of my students.
And he had a young
kid in his household.
And I said, Neil, you
sure you want to do this?
Maybe you should let me
run a few more simulations.
And he said, no, no, no.
My wife is cool.
I think we're ready to do this.
I felt guilty enough that
I invested a small amount
in the friends-and-family round.
And in retrospect,
I wish I would
have invested a lot more because
that's probably my single most
profitable investment.
In 2017, this company,
BridgeBio Pharma,
came out of stealth mode.
And we had our first investor
was not a venture capitalist,
but a private equity firm
that prior to this company
had never invested in biotech.
The company is called KKR.
You may have heard of them.
Some of you undoubtedly will
be doing internships with them
sometime in the next few years.
We raised about $40 million
in that very first round
after the
friends-and-family round.
A year later, we
raised another 135,
a year later, yet another 300.
So we were right around the
$400 to $500 million range.
We had about 15 projects,
just like the simulations.
And at that point, we did
an IPO, and after the IPO,
we raised another 750.
And as of this morning,
or early this morning,
before the market
opened, BridgeBio
is currently trading at about
$4.6 billion of market cap.
All of the investors,
myself included,
have done better than we
ever would have expected,
a great rate of return.
But you know what?
That's not what this
company is proud of.
What they are most
proud of is the fact
that there are other
portfolio companies that have
gotten started, thanks to us.
And it's now become a thing that
you can use portfolio theory
to reduce your risk, as this
McKinsey report in 2021 put out.
And at this point, BridgeBio
has about 20 different projects
in the clinic.
Two drugs have
already been approved.
In 2021, a drug focusing
on a very rare kind
of enzyme deficiency, as well as
a rare kind of bile duct cancer.
Both of them were
approved in 2021.
A third blockbuster
drug looks like it's
going to get approved
sometime later this month.
So watch the news for an
announcement from BridgeBio.
And that gene therapy
for that little girl
who had Canavan
disease, that turns out
to be a BridgeBio drug.
And as of last year, that
drug with 10 patients
have shown efficacy in every
single one of the patients that
have the disease.
So we expect that the FDA will
approve that drug sometime
next year.
Really amazing.
And I got to tell you,
the proudest professional
accomplishment that
I've ever experienced
was this moment here when
I met that little girl.
She actually lives in
Boston in Jamaica Plain.
And here she was.
The parents found out
about the business model
that I had developed along with
Neil, and asked to meet with me.
And it was really kind of a
scary and extremely emotional
meeting.
This is the Flour Bakery right
across the Salt and Pepper
Bridge, where Mass General is.
That's where they were
going for their care.
And I went into this
Flour Bakery to meet them.
And my first vision was
walking up the stairs
holding her father's hand.
And she kept pushing
his hand away
because she wanted
to do it on her own.
It's just an extraordinary,
extraordinary moment.
This is the power of
financial engineering.
And let me be very clear.
I had zero to do with any
of the scientific decisions
that BridgeBio made.
I often tell people that
finance cannot turn a bad drug
into a good one.
But the lack of financing, or
the wrong kind of financing,
can easily take a good
drug, and destroy it,
and make sure it never
reaches a patient.
And so finance is an important
aspect of drug development,
but it is not the
most important aspect.
You've got to start
with the science,
and then figure out what
the right financing is.
So I'm going to turn
to my second topic
now, which is energy transition.
I want to illustrate the
fact that finance is not
just about biotech,
but it really
can transform any industry.
And I know a number of you are
concerned about climate change.
So am I. So is Jake and Peter.
And the question is,
what do we do about it?
Now there is this thing
called energy transition.
And there's a report that
I read a couple of years
ago that I highly recommend.
It's a rather harsh
dose of reality.
People talk about
energy transition
like we're going to get
off of fossil fuels soon.
And what this paper argues
is that that's really
not the right term.
We are not taking less and less
of our energy from fossil fuels.
And here's a graph
that illustrates it.
So this is a graph
of how much energy
we are consuming as broken
down by different sources.
So here.
Oil, you can see certainly
natural gas, and coal,
all three forms of fossil
fuels are growing in the amount
that we're consuming
year after year.
Now how can that be?
Because we are making
progress with renewables.
Right?
So here's wind and solar.
This is in blue.
And here is nuclear here.
They're getting a little
bit wider, but not
nearly as fast as
the fossil fuels are.
And it's because human
population is growing.
And also, the kind
of people that we
have on this planet,
that's changing.
We are now having
more and more people
that are moving into
the middle class.
And when you move into the
middle class, what do you want?
You want a better life.
You want a house, you want
two cars instead of one,
you want to take a vacation
by flying somewhere.
All of the things that
you and I take for
granted, there are
millions to hundreds
of millions of people that
are for the first time,
being able to experience it.
And that's why the
consumption of energy
is growing far faster
than our ability
to create non-greenhouse-gas
sources of energy.
So the problem with
energy transition
is that if you just
look at what's going on,
we can't just rely
on renewable energy.
We need to have low-carbon
forms of energy that
don't pollute the atmosphere,
and that are on demand,
available.
So what are we doing?
How are we transitioning from
one energy source to another?
It's not really transitioning.
We're not declining our usage
of these kinds of sources
of energy, but we need
to be adding to them
with low-carbon sources.
And so from what my experts
in energy, my colleagues here
in the geo department
are telling me,
they're telling me that there
are three sources of energy that
is non-renewable.
They're not wind and solar,
but they are ultimately
going to be infinite,
close-to-infinite,
sources of energy.
And that is fusion,
fission, and geothermal.
And for a variety
of reasons, we're
not going to see
a lot of progress
in the near term for fission.
We already have
nuclear power plants.
But the problem from a
political point of view
is nobody wants to have
them near where they live.
And nobody wants to deal
with the mess of the fuels
that ultimately,
when they degrade,
become radioactive
and dangerous.
So because the prices of fossil
fuels are highly path dependent,
this energy transition is very,
very difficult to predict.
And what that
tells us is we need
to start thinking about
alternative sources of energy
that are going to
be sustainable.
And so it turns out
that nuclear energy
is the main source
of sustainable
energy for the long-term
future of the human species.
And there are only two forms
of nuclear energy, fusion
and fission.
So as you probably know, fusion
is when we split an atom,
and you get more energy
out than you put in.
But fusion energy is where
you squeeze atoms together.
And it turns out that
the squeezing gives you
a lot more energy than
the splitting of an atom.
It also turns out
that fusion energy
is the most abundant form of
energy in the entire universe.
Why?
Because this is
what powers stars,
and that's where we
get all of our energy
other than geothermal.
It's basically we're
getting energy from the sun.
So fusion, turns
out, can produce
roughly 4 times more energy per
kilogram of fuel than fission.
And here's the kicker
it does not produce
long-lasting radioactive waste.
When you are finished using
fission-based energy systems
like uranium, plutonium, you
will have radioactive waste that
in some cases have a half
life of 100,000 years,
which is a lot longer
than I plan to live.
So that's the problem.
Whereas with fusion energy,
it produces water, and helium,
and maybe some tritium,
which is radioactive.
But it doesn't last that long.
And moreover,
tritium is something
that we need as part
of our fusion inputs.
So the problem with fusion is
you need three things to happen,
the so-called Lawson
triple product.
You need to take a
compound, some matter,
and you need to squeeze
it together really
hard because that's how you're
going to get atoms to fuse.
Unfortunately, just squeezing
it is not enough on this planet.
You have to loosen them up so
that they will come together.
And that means you have
to heat it to a very, very
high temperature.
And then you have
to hold on to it
for a long enough period of time
so that the fusion reactions can
happen.
So these are the
three things that
have to happen, temperature,
pressure, and time.
Now it turns out that on
the sun, or in the sun,
this happens relatively easily.
The pressure gets created
by gravitational pull.
And the temperature
increases as a function
of how it pulls in
through the gravity,
the different combustible items.
And as we know, once
you ignite fusion,
it lasts, and lasts, and
lasts for many, many hundreds
of thousands to
millions of years.
So something pretty amazing
happened here in Cambridge
on Labor Day weekend, 2021.
What happened is that
MIT, in collaboration
with a spin off that it created
called Commonwealth Fusion
Systems, they created
a magnetic field
that was so strong, that
it will, in principle, be
able to contain fusion
reactions to the degree
that we need in order
to achieve ignition.
It can actually
light this plasma.
And this demonstration occurred
about five blocks from here
on Albany Street.
They created a 20-tesla magnet.
20-tesla magnet.
That is an extremely
strong magnetic field.
And the interesting thing
about what happened here
is that three months later--
and by the way,
this is yours truly.
I was there for this event.
I collaborated with Dennis
Whyte, the head of the Plasma
Science and Fusion Center.
So he kindly invited
me to be there.
This was, by the way, Sunday
morning at 7:30 AM Labor Day
weekend.
I was out on the
Cape with my family.
And I abandoned
them to come here.
That's how nerdy I was.
But it was an extraordinary
historical event.
What happened after
that, of course, was we
saw that the Lawrence
Livermore Laboratory, Berkeley,
they actually created a
truly exothermic fusion
reaction, meaning
more power came out
than money went than energy went
in, which basically says you're
creating money out of nothing.
If money is energy, then
you're putting more money--
you're getting more money
out than you're putting in.
Also, the regulatory
authorities have
agreed that fusion should not be
regulated the way that fission
is, which is pretty big.
And yet another repeat
of fusion in 2023.
So the question that my
colleague in the Plasma Science
and Fusion Center, Dennis
Whyte, and I have asked
is, can we use finance
to fund fusion?
So we wrote a paper
about this too.
And in this paper,
we do a calculation
that shows, yes, there is a path
of creating a portfolio in order
to fund fusion.
Now a portfolio of what?
So I have to answer
that question.
In order for me to answer
a question about portfolio
of what, I have to
describe, what do I
mean by saying, fusion?
What do we mean by fusion?
What I mean is to create a
commercially-viable power
plant, a reactor, that will
generate enough heat to create
a turbine that will spin
and generate electrons
to be put on the power grid.
That's what I call, fusion.
And so what that means
is you need this.
You need a fusion reactor
that will do its thing
and generate heat.
The heat will basically heat up
water, water will turn to steam.
That will basically
cause turbines to spin.
As the turbines spin,
you generate electricity,
and the electricity goes
on existing power grids.
So this whole thing is
what I'm calling, fusion.
That's what I want to do.
That's what I want to invest in.
Now how do we do that?
How do we invest in fusion?
And the answer has
to do with what
it takes to achieve fusion
electrons on the grid.
These are all the
components that experts
tell me are needed in order
to get fusion to happen.
And so the question
is, how do we do that?
And the answer,
like anything else,
is break it apart,
look at it one by one,
and figure out what
you need in order
to achieve these
different components.
So one of the things
we need is sustained
high-temperature plasma.
So plasma is a fourth
state of matter.
When you heat something up
to a certain temperature,
it becomes plasma.
The problem is as
it gets hotter,
it's harder and harder to
contain this kind of matter.
And so you need to have
some way to hold on to it.
Well, magnetic bottles
are what we're considering
in one form of fusion.
But if that's the
issue of creating
high-temperature
plasma, then let's
take it and break it apart.
What do we need just to do that?
And by the way,
just to let you know
what high temperature
means, we're
talking about 100
million degrees.
100 million degrees.
That's hot.
So how do we achieve that?
Well, it turns out that
there are a bunch of things
you need in order to do it.
So what do we do?
This is the portfolio
I'm talking about.
I'm talking about creating
a portfolio of technology
that, when combined, will
allow you to achieve fusion.
But even if never combined, they
have value in and of itself.
For example, advanced
vacuum systems.
It turns out that
in order to achieve
really high
temperatures, you have
to have ultra-pure conditions
with no contaminants and no air,
in particular.
You need to have a
vacuum system that
works far better than your
typical Hoover vacuum cleaner.
It turns out that if you can
create that vacuum system,
it has applications in many
other things, like for example,
in drug development.
And so if you think about
fusion not as one thing,
but as a portfolio of a whole
bunch of different technologies
that have value in
and of themselves,
but that when combined,
will have value for fusion,
you can basically
break it apart and do
the kind of financial
analysis that we just
did with a single drug
development project,
and then put them into a
portfolio, maybe 150 of them,
and figure out the
risk and reward,
and be able to finance it.
So the idea is to create a
multibillion dollar fusion
mega fund, just like we did
with the cancer mega fund,
and finance all these
different technologies.
And imagine creating an
incredible board of advisors.
On the scientific
side, you've got people
like Mike Campbell, University
of Rochester expert in laser
technology, Steve Chu, former
energy secretary, Nobel Prize
winner, Rob Goldston, Dave
Larbalestier, Ernest Moniz, also
another former Energy Secretary
that was an MIT faculty
member, Dennis Whyte, the former
head of the Plasma Science
and Fusion Center, and so on.
And then on the
business side, you've
got people like Sam Altman,
Jeff Bezos, Peter Diamandis,
Bill Gates, Vinod Khosla,
so on, and so forth,
people that can actually help
us manage the business models.
Now you might say,
well, wait a minute.
How are you going
to get these people
to be part of this effort?
And that's a challenge,
because the folks in blue,
they're not motivated by money.
So if I call them up and
ask them to be part of this,
I would doubt that they would
even return my phone calls.
They've never heard of me.
The folks in green,
they have all the money.
And so I'm pretty sure that, and
actually I know a number of them
already.
So that's why I know
that if I call them,
they will not return
my phone calls.
But if you raise multi-billion
dollars to deploy capital,
all of them will
return your phone call,
not just because of the money.
As I said, the people in blue,
they don't care about money.
And the people in green,
they have all the money.
They don't need your money.
But if you can actually
show that there's
a business path that
allows you to achieve
your goal of ignition, they'll
all want to be part of it.
And finally, how many of you, if
I created a fund like this with
these people, how many of
you would put as a one-time
investment, just
one-time investment,
$1,500 of your 401(k) money
that you may have saved up after
a summer internship or after
your first year working
at your job?
How many of you would put
1,500 into a fusion fund?
That's where I'm going to get
the multi-billions of dollars,
because with 130 million
households out there,
if 3% of you put in $1,500,
that's more than $30 billion
right there.
We can do this.
This can actually be done.
So there are many
other examples of this.
Yeah.
Question.
AUDIENCE: Wouldn't the
portfolio for the fusion of all
those different
things, wouldn't they
be highly correlated these
different industries as opposed
to the drugs [INAUDIBLE]?
ANDREW W. LO: Well,
that's a great question.
Let's go back and
take a look at it.
So it's true that
the entire fusion
reactors of many different
companies will be correlated.
But they will not be
perfectly correlated
if they're using different
ways of achieving fusion.
One uses magnetic, the
other one uses inertial.
And so there are
different technologies.
But more importantly, if
I look at this portfolio
of technologies, so one of
them is plasma heating systems,
how to make things really hot.
The second one is
advanced vacuum systems,
how to keep things
really clean and pure.
A third one is magnetic
confinement technologies,
so how do you shape
the magnets in order
to keep the bottle
from becoming unstable.
Each of those things have
nothing to do with each other.
AUDIENCE: Oh, right.
OK.
I thought they might.
That's all.
OK, that makes sense now.
ANDREW W. LO: Yeah, the
technology, some of them do.
But most of them do not.
And that's where you're going
to get the diversification.
You're right.
So lots of other technologies.
The key to all of these are
that they are long shots.
Very, very low probability, or
unknown probability, of success.
They cost a lot of money,
they take a lot of time,
but the returns to
society are huge.
And so that's why you need
to have innovative financing
for these long shots.
The key to all of this is
to have the right narrative,
the right story
to tell investors,
about how you're
going to give them
a return on their investment.
And that requires the
right business models
to be able to do that.
So I'm going to wrap up with a
story that I use lots of times,
because when I first heard it, I
was so impressed that I decided
that that was going to be my
motivation for doing what I'm
doing.
It has to do with this man,
Professor Harvey Lodish.
He's a biology faculty
member here at MIT
in the Whitehead Institute.
Harvey, when he was an
assistant professor in 1983,
he was approached by
a businessman asking
whether he would collaborate
with him to create
a treatment for a rare disease
called Gaucher's syndrome.
This is also one of these
genetic typos, which
prevents your body
from producing
important housekeeping enzymes.
And without this
enzyme, fatty acids
build up in your spleen,
your bone marrow.
And by the time
you're a teenager,
if you have a very serious
version of this disease,
you're dead.
And so Harvey and
his colleagues, they
developed the treatment
to deal with this disease
by replacing the enzyme with an
artificially-developed version
of it.
And this little
company in 1991 got
a drug called Ceredase
approved by the FDA,
the first-ever enzyme
replacement therapy.
They would just put back into
these individuals' bodies
the missing enzyme that
their bodies don't produce.
They can produce it outside,
and give it to them.
And you may have heard of
Harvey's little company.
It's called Genzyme.
And in 2014, Genzyme
was purchased by Sanofi
for $20 billion.
Now that's not why I want to be
Harvey Lodish, although that's
not a bad reason, by the way.
I'm an economist, after all.
See, I want to be Harvey because
of what happened in 2002.
In that year,
Harvey's daughter was
pregnant with her
second child, Harvey
and his wife's second
grandchild, a boy named Andrew.
Great name, by the way.
Andrew was diagnosed in
utero with Gaucher syndrome.
What are the chances of that?
So I talked to
Harvey about this.
I asked him.
It was a very
emotional conversation.
I asked him, Harvey, did you
know in 1983, when you started
Genzyme, that you would
be developing a drug that
would someday save the life of
your as-yet-unborn grandson?
And Harvey said, no.
He had no idea.
He said, I thought that if I
could do some cool science,
and help some patients,
that would be great.
1983 was two decades before
the human genome was sequenced.
So I had no idea that I
was carrying the mutation.
And in 2012, when
his son turned 10,
he developed the full-blown
symptoms of Gaucher's.
So he would be dead if
it weren't for the drug
that grandpa developed.
That's why I want
to be Harvey Lodish.
I don't have an MD or a
PhD in molecular biology.
I will never be able to
develop a drug that will save
my as-yet-unborn grandchildren.
But I realized something.
I realized that you know what?
We can all be
Harvey Lodish if we
invest in the drugs that save
our as-yet-unborn grandchildren.
Finance doesn't always
have to be a zero-sum game
if we don't let it.
With the right business
models, the right scale
at the right time,
we can do the thing
that everybody says they want
to do, but very few of us
ever get to do, which
is that we can actually
do well by doing good.
And with your help, we
can actually do this
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
[CRESCENDO]
Thank you.
I teach MBA students, so I
have to use sound effects.
I'm sorry.
Thank you.
We have some time for questions?
PROFESSOR: Sure.
Yeah.
ANDREW W. LO: Yeah,
questions or comments?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, [INAUDIBLE].
I know you mentioned
about when you're
talking about the
[INAUDIBLE] partners, when
you talk about the payout
from 10 years, 11, to 20.
ANDREW W. LO: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: And you're saying
that that [INAUDIBLE]
is one month, how long
does a patent last.
ANDREW W. LO: That's right.
AUDIENCE: So I was
wondering after you said
that, other people [INAUDIBLE].
I guess I wasn't sure about
how that whole process works.
But after you [INAUDIBLE]
ANDREW W. LO: Sure.
So when you have a patent,
it gives you the right
to use the information in
the patent exclusively,
meaning nobody else is allowed
to use that information.
And so typically for drugs,
what is that information?
It's basically a
chemical formula
for a particular
compound that doesn't
exist in nature naturally.
You created it, you
came up with it,
you filed a patent disclosure.
And the patent office said,
yep, this is new, and useful.
We're going to grant
you the patent.
So for 20 years, only you
are allowed to use that idea.
And so when you use that
idea to create a drug,
you're the only one that's
allowed to make the drug.
And so if people want that
drug, they got to pay you.
And so you end up
charging a price
for the drug that will generate
a lot of value for you.
At the end of the 20
years, what's the deal?
The deal is everybody
gets to use that idea.
And so now, you've got companies
that can produce the drug.
Because typically, the
producing of the drug
is pretty cheap, right?
Once you give me the
formula, I can basically
get a chemical manufacturing
plant to come up with it
relatively cheaply,
a few pennies a pill.
The expensive part was
developing the clinical trials
to get the FDA to give
you the license to do it.
Once that's done, it's
all profits for you
until such time as
now everybody gets
to produce it for relatively
low amounts of money.
So it's like aspirin.
At one point,
aspirin was patented.
Now anybody can make it because
you could look up the patent.
There's the formula right there.
You can do it yourself if you
know how to mix those chemicals.
And you don't have to
pay anybody for it.
But before the patent
expires, you're
not allowed to use the idea.
Or if you want to
use the idea, you
have to pay the
owner of the patent
a fee for using their idea.
That's how it works.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: How do you find
these investment opportunities?
How do you even begin to
research these [INAUDIBLE]?
ANDREW W. LO: Yeah, that's
a great, great question.
The answer is you need
to have expertise.
So as I mentioned, Neil Kumar,
the co-founder of BridgeBio,
and the person who
created it really,
Neil has a PhD in
chemical engineering.
But he didn't go off and
become a chemical engineer.
He went off and first
worked at McKinsey,
advising biotech companies
about their corporate strategy.
And ultimately, he
decided to start
investing in various
different ideas
because he had the expertise.
As a chemical engineer, you
have the science background,
the engineering
background, and then
as you work in the
industry, you learn
about how the industry works.
So you learn that aspect of it.
That's what gives
you the expertise.
And then once you have the
expertise, the companies that
have the money to invest,
the venture capital
firms, the private
equity firms, even
the big pharma companies
that have corporate venture
divisions, they will
want to hire you
to help them manage the money.
That's how you ultimately
end up being able to do that.
You got to have the expertise.
And by the way, that's
one of the reasons why
MIT graduates are so popular
among Wall Street investment
houses, because you all
not only have expertise,
but you have the ability
to learn and develop
new expertise as needed.
That's really important.
Yes.
AUDIENCE: How do
we invest in this?
ANDREW W. LO: What's that.
AUDIENCE: How do
we invest in this?
ANDREW W. LO: How do you invest?
Well, that's actually
the same question I have.
How do I invest in you?
You all are the next generation
of investment opportunities.
And I'm not saying this
just to flatter you.
This is a biological fact.
You are going to be around a lot
longer than Jake, Peter, and I.
And therefore, all of you
are the future of innovation.
And so, yes.
I would love to figure
out how you invest.
In terms of investing in
these kind of companies,
the biotech companies, well,
BridgeBio is publicly traded.
So anybody can invest.
And I'm not suggesting
you should invest in them.
There's risk, very, very
high risk, by the way,
in biotech companies.
So you need to be very
careful about that.
But the much harder
areas to invest
are the private companies,
because by definition, they're
private.
So you don't know
as much about them
as publicly-traded
companies where
you've got a lot of
published information.
And you probably are already
aware, but if you're not,
you should be, that MIT is an
incredibly attractive place
for private investors
to come and look
for opportunities among the
students and the faculty.
You are in a wonderful
position, particularly
those of you who are
majoring in math,
because your skills are portable
to virtually every industry
out there.
I don't know of an industry
that doesn't need math.
Maybe the Hollywood
film industry.
But you've got to count
your money somehow.
Tom Cruise has to
count his money.
So you got to have
math for that.
So I think that there are lots
of venture capitalists hanging
around Kendall Square and
MIT to try to understand
whether they can invest in you.
You will find that to be a very,
very interesting phenomenon.
Yeah, I'll come back to you.
But you were first.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] thing
that you want to invest in,
these groups already exist that
are trying to use these things,
but they need money.
Or is it that the
investment going
towards starting XYZ that
does this specific thing?
ANDREW W. LO: Well,
there is still
a valley of death in
the sense that there
are lots of groups
that want money
to do the kind of cool
things that you are all going
to come up with on your own.
By the way, to put in a
plug for Dennis Whyte,
he teaches a course on
nuclear engineering,
where as part of
the course, they
come up with ideas,
a number of which
ultimately end up becoming
commercialized and real
startups.
So there are a
number of companies
that can't get funded because
of the valley of death.
MIT has a much
better opportunity
set than if you were, say, at
Duke University or University
of North Carolina.
That's part of the research
triangle down south.
And they've got some really
cool ideas, smart students,
and faculty as well.
But because they're not part of
the Boston, Cambridge ecosystem,
they don't have as many
venture capitalists down there
looking to fund various
different projects.
So I would say that
there are still
lots and lots of smaller groups
that are looking for funding
that can't get it because
they just don't know enough
about the financing.
So what I've described to you
now, in just this one class,
is probably more information
than most startup groups have
in terms of thinking
about risk rewards,
and trade offs like that.
Yes.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE],
you're also a professor here.
So I was wondering [INAUDIBLE]
and stuff like that here at MIT?
Or is that something
that [INAUDIBLE]?
ANDREW W. LO: So again, very
glad you asked that question,
because I happen to be teaching
a class right now on health
care financing.
It's called 15.482.
Now for those of
you who may not be
able to take that class because
of conflicts or whatever,
that class is actually online.
It's part of MIT's
Open Learning Library.
So there is a version of 482x
that you can all sign up for.
It's free.
There's an archived
version of it.
So just check on the Open
Learning Library website.
It's not part of OCW, but
Open Learning Library.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: So the gentleman
who started [INAUDIBLE],
can you just give a rough
outline of how on Earth he
did that from a PhD?
[INAUDIBLE]
ANDREW W. LO: Sure.
So the first thing he did
when he graduated was he
went to McKinsey, a
consulting company.
And he knew a lot of
science and engineering,
but he didn't know much
about the industry.
As part of McKinsey's program,
they train their hires
to learn about the industry.
So probably for
the first year, he
shadowed a more experienced
biopharma consultant
that brought him into
various different companies
and showed him projects
that they were working on,
and how he could add to those
projects by doing research.
Just like if he were a chemical
engineer doing research
on better ways of
refining oil, he'd
have to go and read articles,
and then talk to people,
and then do experiments.
In that same way, if you're in
a consulting firm like McKinsey,
and you're working
on a project like,
how should Pfizer fund their
vaccine program for RSV?
Well, what would he do?
He would go and learn about
RSV, he would read the journal
articles, he would figure out
how it's being funded now,
he would come up
with new ideas, he
would try to test them out by
writing different simulation
examples to illustrate
what could happen.
Those are the kind of things
that he did for the first three
to five years of his career.
At some point, he learned
enough about the industry
to start making
investment decisions,
like, this company has got a
good bet, because all the things
that I was studying about
proper ways of funding
particular projects, they're
doing it versus this company,
I don't really want to invest
because they don't even
understand how to fund
their internal pipeline.
So at some point,
he left McKinsey
to join Third Rock Ventures,
which is a biotech venture
capital company.
And then he spent a few
years there learning
how to make investments.
It was at Third Rock that he
approached me and said, look,
I've been thinking about
rare diseases as well.
I've seen investments
that Third Rock
has passed on because it's not
a so-called platform technology.
It's only a one-trick pony, one
idea, one drug, one disease.
And Third Rock thought
it was too risky.
Would you be willing to
run some models with me
to fund those projects?
And after we ran a
bunch of simulations,
it gave him enough
conviction that this
was going to be a
profitable venture that he
was willing to take the
risk to try to do that.
And the first
thing we did was we
asked Third Rock,
you guys passed
on these three opportunities.
Do you mind if we take them?
Can we invest in them?
Third Rock said, be my guest.
Go for it.
And what was not
appropriate for Third Rock,
given they've got lots
of other opportunities
that they're focusing on,
was a great opportunity
set for BridgeBio,
this portfolio company.
So like anything else, it's
a gradual process where you
learn more, and more, and more.
And sometimes, at
some point, you
learn so much, that you
are confident that you
know enough to be able to
start your own company.
AUDIENCE: That's great.
Thank you so much.
ANDREW W. LO: Yeah, sure.
By the way, it doesn't
mean it's any less scary.
There is still a
scary moment where
you've learned all
this stuff, but still,
quitting your job with a baby
at home, and bills to pay,
that is scary.
But at some point, your
confidence and your ability
to get through that scary
period outweighs the wall
that your emotions put up.
Yes.
AUDIENCE: I have a question
about in times of crisis
or when you actually
need some type of growth,
or for example like a COVID-19
vaccine or you need [INAUDIBLE].
I guess, because you talked
about the [INAUDIBLE] and all
that stuff.
Is that during those times?
How is it adjusted?
I would say, or if you can get
into how it's like [INAUDIBLE].
ANDREW W. LO: Well, so that's
a really important observation,
because in the case of COVID-19,
we did have a valley of death.
And we still do have
a valley of death
when it comes to vaccines,
because the profitability
of the typical vaccine
is not very attractive.
And so prior to COVID,
most big pharma companies
were actually getting out
of the vaccine business.
Cancer was much more profitable.
Rare diseases actually ended
up being more profitable
than vaccines.
And so right before
the pandemic hit,
there were only four big
pharma companies left
that were still in the
vaccine-making business.
And but once the
pandemic hit, and we
knew that it was going to be
bad, when it came on US shores
in March of 2020, we knew
it was going to be bad.
At that point, a lot
of things started
to happen all at the same time.
First of all,
philanthropy had been
funding scientific experiments
for vaccines for decades,
in particular, the
Gates Foundation.
They, for years,
have been working
on a vaccine for malaria.
Still doesn't exist, by the way.
We still don't have a vaccine
for malaria, believe it or not.
Malaria is probably the single
biggest killer around the world.
Not here in the
US, but in Africa,
where malaria is a real problem
for many, many countries.
And it kills literally
millions of people every year.
So the Gates Foundation had been
working on that for many years,
funding scientific research, and
funding Moderna in particular,
among other companies.
And so once the
vaccine hit US soil,
we were very, very quick
to be able to collaborate
with international
scientists to get
the sequence, the
genetic sequence,
of the particular spike
protein that we're
going to target with the
various different antibodies.
So that process
worked like magic.
There was no valley of death
for that period of time,
because the government
stepped in and said,
we got to do something,
otherwise, lots of people
are going to die.
For the very first time in
the history of the industry,
it took 63 days from the time
we sequenced the COVID-19 virus
to when the first human patient
was injected with the vaccine
candidate, 63 days.
Typically, it takes three to
five years to create a vaccine.
It took us 63 days.
That's an example of what you're
talking about getting around
the valley of death.
The problem is now that COVID
seems like it's over, of course,
it's not really over.
You can still get
COVID-19, as many of you
will find out in
the next few months.
But it's not as serious.
We know how to deal with it.
We've got a number of
drugs and treatments.
And we recognize the
various different symptoms.
So because it is
not that serious,
people are more
relaxed about it.
And what that means is the
valley of death is back.
People don't want to
spend money on it.
They'd rather spend
money on, guess what?
AI.
Right?
Let's put money in OpenAI,
or Anthropic, or any one
of these other companies.
And that's a problem.
So I think that we need
to worry about that.
That's one of the reasons
why I'm here today,
to try to get some of you
to be excited about taking
your ideas, and your toolkits,
and doing well by doing good.
You will really do
spectacularly well,
from a financial point
of view, if you're
able to succeed in fusion, or
in drug development devices,
and so on.
But even more
importantly, you're
going to feel really good
about what you're doing.
And you're going to actually
help a lot of people.
All right.
I'm out of time.
So thank you very much,
and have a good day.
AUDIENCE: Thank you.